Nicholas J. Lavnikevich Papers VHP2004/3
CCSU Veterans History Project
Nicholas J. Lavnikevich Papers
Bulk, 1943
1943, 2004-5
VHP2004/3
CCSU Veterans History Project
24.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Lavnikevich, Nicholas John
Biographical Note
Born in Readville, MA on March of 1920 Nicholas Lavnikevich enlisted in the U.S. Navy in August of 1942 while living in Boston, Massachusetts. As Chief Pharmacist Mate Nicholas served aboard the “Xsurg or YP-417 (Yard Patrol 417),” a reconverted fishing vessel which patrolled the east cost of the United States, New Caledonia, the Fiji Islands, the Solomon Islands and New Hebrides. Nicholas also served aboard the USS Wintle, a destroyer escort troop transport, at the time, bound for the United States. Nicholas is a recipient of the Navy Good Conduct Medal, the American Campaign medal, the Asiatic-Pacific Theater medal, the WWII Victory medal, and the Navy Combat Action Ribbon. He was discharged from the U.S. Navy in October of 1945.
Arrangement Note
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into 3 series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Publications
Series III, Multi-media
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Online Access
An Online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
United States. Navy.; USS YP-417 (patrol craft).; Bora-Bora (island); Guadalcanal (Solomon Islands); Guadalcanal, Battle of, Solomon Islands, 1942-1943; Medicine, Navy; Military hospitals; Veterans - - Connecticut - - interviews; World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area
- Series I: Personal Paers
  - Synopsis of oral history interview with Nicholas Lavnikevich, Jan. 30, 2004; 2004/3.I.1
- Series II: Publications
  - Only medical man aboard pacific ship, 1943; 2004/3.II.1
  - Local bluejacket serves on trawler in the Solomon, Circa 1943; 2004/3.II.2
  - Hub trawlers now serving in Solomons, Undate; 2004/3.II.3
- Series III: Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images
    - Nicholas Lavnikevich aboard patrol craft U.S.S. YP-417 in the South Pacific, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.1
    - Patrol craft U.S.S. YP-417, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.2
    - Group of recently initiated "shellbacks", 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.3
    - Mail call on board patrol craft, U.S.S. YP-417, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.4
    - Navy personnel relaxing on board patrol craft, U.S.S. YP-417, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.5
    - Officers of the U.S.S. YP-417, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.6
    - The “Black Gang” (engine room personnel) on board patrol craft, U.S.S. YP-417, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.7
    - members on board U.S.S. YP-417, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.8
    - U.S.S. YP-417 Gunner Mates, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.9
    - Four sailors in a melon garden on Florida Island, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.10
    - Nicholas Lavnikevich in a melon garden on Florida Island, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.11
    - Nicholas Lavnikevich and Bill Corey on Florida Island, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.12
    - Enjoying entertainment on Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.13
    - Two American Tank Landing Ships, one is bellowing smoke after being struck by Japanese planes, Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.14
    - U.S. Army medic Charles Bourgeois and an unidentified enlisted man, 52nd Naval Hospital, Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.15
    - U.S. Army Medic Charles Bourgeois (left) and Nicholas Lavnikevich (right), 52nd Field Hospital, Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.16
    - 52nd Field Hospital, Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.17
    - Grave of D. A. Joy in American military cemetery, Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.18
    - Side by side photographs, each depicting Nicholas Lavnikevich while stationed at the 52nd Field Hospital, Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.19
    - American servicemen assisting a Japanese soldier on Guadalcanal, 1943; 2004/3.IIIa.20
  - Subseries B: Moving Images
    - Oral history interview with Nicholas Lavnikevich, Jan 30, 2004; 2004/3.IIIb.1 (Disk DVD VHP2004/3, Box VHP Interview 1)
      Existence and Location of Copies note
      Interview video also available online.
      Streaming Video